<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: python3 | The digital cat]]></title>
  <link href="http://lgiordani.com/blog/categories/python3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lgiordani.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-20T15:18:11+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://lgiordani.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Leonardo Giordani]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python 3 OOP Part 3 - Delegation: composition and inheritance]]></title>
    <link href="http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-3-delegation-composition-and-inheritance/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T15:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-3-delegation-composition-and-inheritance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--more-->


<h2>Previous post</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-2-classes-and-members">Python 3 OOP Part 2 - Classes and members</a></p>

<h2>The Delegation Run</h2>

<p>If classes are objects what is the difference between types and instances?</p>

<p>When I talk about "my cat" I am referring to a concrete instance of the "cat" concept, which is a <em>subtype</em> of "animal". So, despite being both objects, while types can be <em>specialized</em>, instances cannot.</p>

<p>Usually an object B is said to be a specialization of an object A when:</p>

<ul>
<li>B has all the features of A</li>
<li>B can provide new features</li>
<li>B can perform some or all the tasks performed by A in a different way</li>
</ul>


<p>Those targets are very general and valid for any system and the key to achieve them with the maximum reuse of already existing components is <em>delegation</em>. Delegation means that an object shall perform only what it knows best, and leave the rest to other objects.</p>

<p>Delegation can be implemented with two different mechanisms: <em>composition</em> and <em>inheritance</em>. Sadly, very often only inheritance is listed among the pillars of OOP techniques, forgetting that it is an implementation of the more generic and fundamental mechanism of delegation; perhaps a better nomenclature for the two techniques could be <em>explicit delegation</em> (composition) and <em>implicit delegation</em> (inheritance).</p>

<p>Please note that, again, when talking about composition and inheritance we are talking about focusing on a behavioural or structural delegation. Another way to think about the difference between composition and inheritance is to consider if the object <em>knows</em> who can satisfy your request or if the object <em>is</em> the one that satisfy the request.</p>

<p><strong>Please, please, please do not forget composition</strong>: in many cases, composition can lead to simpler systems, with benefits on maintainability and changeability.</p>

<p>Usually composition is said to be a very generic technique that needs no special syntax, while inheritance and its rules are strongly dependent on the language of choice. Actually, the strong dynamic nature of Python softens the boundary line between the two techniques.</p>

<h2>Inheritance Now</h2>

<p>In Python a class can be declared as an <em>extension</em> of one or more different classes, through the <em>class inheritance</em> mechanism. The child class (the one that inherits) has the same internal structure of the parent class (the one that is inherited), and for the case of multiple inheritance the language has very specific rules to manage possible conflicts or redefinitions among the parent classes. A very simple example of inheritance is</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor(Door):</p>

<pre><code>pass
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>where we declare a new class <code>SecurityDoor</code> that, at the moment, is a perfect copy of the <code>Door</code> class. Let us investigate what happens when we access attributes and methods. First we instance the class</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>sdoor = SecurityDoor(1, 'closed')
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>The first check we can do is that class attributes are still global and shared</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>SecurityDoor.colour is Door.colour
True
sdoor.colour is Door.colour
True
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>This shows us that Python tries to resolve instance members not only looking into the class the instance comes from, but also investigating the parent classes. In this case <code>sdoor.colour</code> becomes <code>SecurityDoor.colour</code>, that in turn becomes <code>Door.colour</code>. <code>SecurityDoor</code> <em>is</em> a <code>Door</code>.</p>

<p>If we investigate the content of <code>__dict__</code> we can catch a glimpse of the inheritance mechanism in action</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>sdoor.<strong>dict</strong>
{'number': 1, 'status': 'closed'}
sdoor.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>
mappingproxy({'<strong>doc</strong>': None, '<strong>module</strong>': '<strong>main</strong>'})
Door.<strong>dict</strong>
mappingproxy({'<strong>dict</strong>': <attribute '__dict__' of 'Door' objects>,</p>

<pre><code>'colour': 'yellow',
'open': &lt;function Door.open at 0xb687e224&gt;,
'__init__': &lt;function Door.__init__ at 0xb687e14c&gt;,
'__doc__': None,
'close': &lt;function Door.close at 0xb687e1dc&gt;,
'knock': &lt;classmethod object at 0xb67ff6ac&gt;,
'__weakref__': &lt;attribute '__weakref__' of 'Door' objects&gt;,
'__module__': '__main__',
'paint': &lt;classmethod object at 0xb67ff6ec&gt;})
</code></pre>

<p>```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>As you can see the content of <code>__dict__</code> for <code>SecurityDoor</code> is very narrow compared to that of <code>Door</code>. The inheritance mechanism takes care of the missing elements by climbing up the classes tree. Where does Python get the parent classes? A class always contains a <code>__bases__</code> tuple that lists them</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>SecurityDoor.<strong>bases</strong>
(<class '__main__.Door'>,)
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>So an example of what Python does to resolve a class method call through the inheritance tree is</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>sdoor.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>bases</strong>[0].<strong>dict</strong>['knock'].<strong>get</strong>(sdoor)
<bound method type.knock of <class '__main__.SecurityDoor'>>
sdoor.knock
<bound method type.knock of <class '__main__.SecurityDoor'>>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Please note that this is just an example that does not consider multiple inheritance.</p>

<p>Let us try now to override some methods and attributes. In Python you can <em>override</em> (redefine) a parent class member simply by redefining it in the child class.</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor(Door):</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'gray'
locked = True

def open(self):
    if not self.locked:
        self.status = 'open'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>As you can forecast, the overridden members now are present in the <code>__dict__</code> of the <code>SecurityDoor</code> class</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>SecurityDoor.<strong>dict</strong>
mappingproxy({'<strong>doc</strong>': None,</p>

<pre><code>'__module__': '__main__',
'open': &lt;function SecurityDoor.open at 0xb6fcf89c&gt;,
'colour': 'gray',
'locked': True})
</code></pre>

<p>```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>So when you override a member, the one you put in the child class is used instead of the one in the parent class simply because the former is found before the latter while climbing the class hierarchy. This also shows you that Python does not implicitly call the parent implementation when you override a method. So, overriding is a way to block implicit delegation.</p>

<p>If we want to call the parent implementation we have to do it explicitly. In the former example we could write</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor(Door):</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'gray'
locked = True

def open(self):
    if self.locked:
        return
    Door.open(self)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>You can easily test that this implementation is working correctly.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>sdoor = SecurityDoor(1, 'closed')
sdoor.status
'closed'
sdoor.open()
sdoor.status
'closed'
sdoor.locked = False
sdoor.open()
sdoor.status
'open'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>This form of explicit parent delegation is heavily discouraged, however.</p>

<p>The first reason is because of the very high coupling that results from explicitly naming the parent class again when calling the method. <em>Coupling</em>, in the computer science lingo, means to link two parts of a system, so that changes in one of them directly affect the other one, and is usually avoided as much as possible. In this case if you decide to use a new parent class you have to manually propagate the change to every method that calls it. Moreover, since in Python the class hierarchy can be dynamically changed (i.e. at runtime), this form of explicit delegation could be not only annoying but also wrong.</p>

<p>The second reason is that in general you need to deal with multiple inheritance, where you do not know a priori which parent class implements the original form of the method you are overriding.</p>

<p>To solve these issues, Python supplies the <code>super()</code> built-in function, that climbs the class hierarchy and returns the correct class that shall be called. The syntax for calling <code>super()</code> is</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor(Door):</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'gray'
locked = True

def open(self):
    if self.locked:
        return
    super().open(self)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The output of <code>super()</code> is not exactly the <code>Door</code> class. It returns a <code>super</code> object which representation is <code>&lt;super: &lt;class 'SecurityDoor'&gt;, &lt;SecurityDoor object&gt;&gt;</code>. This object however acts like the parent class, so you can safely ignore its custom nature and use it just like you would do with the <code>Door</code> class in this case.</p>

<h2>Enter the Composition</h2>

<p>Composition means that an object knows another object, and explicitly delegates some tasks to it. While inheritance is implicit, composition is explicit: in Python, however, things are far more interesting than this =).</p>

<p>First of all let us implement classic composition, which simply makes an object part of the other as an attribute</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor:</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'gray'
locked = True

def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.door = Door(number, status)

def open(self):
    if self.locked:
        return
    self.door.open()

def close(self):
    self.door.close()
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The primary goal of composition is to relax the coupling between objects. This little example shows that now <code>SecurityDoor</code> is an <code>object</code> and no more a <code>Door</code>, which means that the internal structure of <code>Door</code> is not copied. For this very simple example both <code>Door</code> and <code>SecurityDoor</code> are not big classes, but in a real system objects can very complex; this means that their allocation consumes a lot of memory and if a system contains thousands or millions of objects that could be an issue.</p>

<p>The composed <code>SecurityDoor</code> has to redefine the <code>colour</code> attribute since the concept of delegation applies only to methods and not to attributes, doesn't it?</p>

<p>Well, no. Python provides a very high degree of indirection for objects manipulation and attribute access is one of the most useful. As you already discovered, accessing attributes is ruled by a special method called <code>__getattribute__()</code> that is called whenever an attribute of the object is accessed. Overriding <code>__getattribute__()</code>, however, is overkill; it is a very complex method, and, being called on every attribute access, any change makes the whole thing slower.</p>

<p>The method we have to leverage to delegate attribute access is <code>__getattr__()</code>, which is a special method that is called whenever the requested attribute is not found in the object. So basically it is the right place to dispatch all attribute and method access our object cannot handle. The previous example becomes</p>

<p>``` python
class SecurityDoor:</p>

<pre><code>locked = True

def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.door = Door(number, status)

def open(self):
    if self.locked:
        return
    self.door.open()

def __getattr__(self, attr):
    return getattr(self.door, attr)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Using <code>__getattr__()</code> blends the separation line between inheritance and composition since after all the former is a form of automatic delegation of every member access.</p>

<p>``` python
class ComposedDoor:</p>

<pre><code>def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.door = Door(number, status)

def __getattr__(self, attr):
    return getattr(self.door, attr)
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>As this last example shows, delegating every member access through <code>__getattr__()</code> is very simple. Pay attention to <code>getattr()</code> which is different from <code>__getattr__()</code>. The former is a built-in that is equivalent to the dotted syntax, i.e. <code>getattr(obj, 'someattr')</code> is the same as <code>obj.someattr</code>, but you have to use it since the name of the attribute is contained in a string.</p>

<p>Composition provides a superior way to manage delegation since it can selectively delegate the access, even mask some attributes or methods, while inheritance cannot. In Python you also avoid the memory problems that might arise when you put many objects inside another; Python handles everything through its reference, i.e. through a pointer to the memory position of the thing, so the size of an attribute is constant and very limited.</p>

<h2>Movie Trivia</h2>

<p>Section titles come from the following movies: <em>The Cannonball Run (1981)</em>, <em>Apocalypse Now (1979)</em>, <em>Enter the Dragon (1973)</em>.</p>

<h2>Sources</h2>

<p>You will find a lot of documentation in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/226ahl/some_links_about_python_oop/">this Reddit post</a>. Most of the information contained in this series come from those sources.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>Feel free to use <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/b/110554719587236016835/110554719587236016835/posts">the blog Google+ page</a> to comment the post. The <a href="https://github.com/lgiordani/lgiordani.github.com/issues">GitHub issues</a> page is the best place to submit corrections.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python 3 OOP Part 2 - Classes and members]]></title>
    <link href="http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-2-classes-and-members/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T14:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-2-classes-and-members</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--more-->


<h2>Previous post</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-1-objects-and-types">Python 3 OOP Part 1 - Objects and types</a></p>

<h2>Python Classes Strike Again</h2>

<p>The Python implementation of classes has some peculiarities. The bare truth is that in Python the class of an object is an object itself. You can check this by issuing <code>type()</code> on the class</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>a = 1
type(a)
<class 'int'>
type(int)
<class 'type'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>This shows that the <code>int</code> class is an object, an instance of the <code>type</code> class.</p>

<p>This concept is not so difficult to grasp as it can seem at first sight: in the real world we deal with <em>concepts</em> using them like <em>things</em>: for example we can talk about the concept of "door", telling people how a door looks like and how it works. In this case the concept of door is the topic of our discussion, so in our everyday experience the <em>type</em> of an object is an object itself. In Python this can be expressed by saying that <em>everything is an object</em>.</p>

<p>If the class of an object is itself an instance it is a concrete object and is stored somewhere in memory. Let us leverage the <em>inspection</em> capabilities of Python and its <code>id()</code> function to check the status of our objects. The <code>id()</code> built-in function returns the memory position of an object.</p>

<p>In the first post we defined this class</p>

<p>``` python
class Door:</p>

<pre><code>def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.number = number
    self.status = status

def open(self):
    self.status = 'open'

def close(self):
    self.status = 'closed'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>First of all, let's create two instances of the <code>Door</code> class and check that the two objects are stored at different addresses</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1 = Door(1, 'closed')
door2 = Door(1, 'closed')
hex(id(door1))
'0xb67e148c'
hex(id(door2))
'0xb67e144c'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>This confirms that the two instances are separate and unrelated.
<strong>Please note that your values are very likely to be different from the ones I got. Being memory addresses they change at every execution.</strong> The second instance was given the same attributes of the first instance to show that the two are different objects regardless of the value of the attributes.</p>

<p>However if we use <code>id()</code> on the class of the two instances we discover that the class is <em>exactly</em> the same</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>hex(id(door1.<strong>class</strong>))
'0xb685f56c'
hex(id(door2.<strong>class</strong>))
'0xb685f56c'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Well this is very important. In Python, a class is not just the schema used to build an object. Rather, the class is a shared living object, which code is accessed at run time.</p>

<p>As we already tested, however, attributes are not stored in the class but in every instance, due to the fact that <code>__init__()</code> works on <code>self</code> when creating them. Classes, however, can be given attributes like any other object; with a terrific effort of imagination, let's call them <em>class attributes</em>.</p>

<p>As you can expect, class attributes are shared among the class instances just like their container</p>

<p>``` python
class Door:</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'brown'

def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.number = number
    self.status = status

def open(self):
    self.status = 'open'

def close(self):
    self.status = 'closed'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Pay attention: the <code>colour</code> attribute here is not created using <code>self</code>, so it is contained in the class and shared among instances</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1 = Door(1, 'closed')
door2 = Door(2, 'closed')
Door.colour
'brown'
door1.colour
'brown'
door2.colour
'brown'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Until here things are not different from the previous case. Let's see if changes of the shared value reflect on all instances</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.colour = 'white'
Door.colour
'white'
door1.colour
'white'
door2.colour
'white'
hex(id(Door.colour))
'0xb67e1500'
hex(id(door1.colour))
'0xb67e1500'
hex(id(door2.colour))
'0xb67e1500'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<h2>Raiders of the Lost Attribute</h2>

<p>Any Python object is automatically given a <code>__dict__</code> attribute, which contains its list of attributes. Let's investigate what this dictionary contains for our example objects:</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.<strong>dict</strong>
mappingproxy({'open': <function Door.open at 0xb68604ac>,</p>

<pre><code>'colour': 'brown',
'__dict__': &lt;attribute '__dict__' of 'Door' objects&gt;,
'__weakref__': &lt;attribute '__weakref__' of 'Door' objects&gt;,
'__init__': &lt;function Door.__init__ at 0xb7062854&gt;,
'__module__': '__main__',
'__doc__': None,
'close': &lt;function Door.close at 0xb686041c&gt;})
</code></pre>

<p>door1.<strong>dict</strong>
{'number': 1, 'status': 'closed'}
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Leaving aside the difference between a dictionary and a <code>mappingproxy</code> object, you can see that the <code>colour</code> attribute is listed among the <code>Door</code> class attributes, while <code>status</code> and <code>number</code> are listed for the instance.</p>

<p>How comes that we can call <code>door1.colour</code>, if that attribute is not listed for that instance? This is a job performed by the magic <code>__getattribute__()</code> method; in Python the dotted syntax automatically invokes this method so when we write <code>door1.colour</code>, Python executes <code>door1.__getattribute__('colour')</code>. That method performs the  <em>attribute  lookup</em> action, i.e. finds the value of the attribute by looking in different places.</p>

<p>The standard implementation of <code>__getattribute__()</code> searches first the internal dictionary (<code>__dict__</code>) of an object, then the type of the object itself; in this case <code>door1.__getattribute__('colour')</code> executes first <code>door1.__dict__['colour']</code> and then, since the latter raises a <code>KeyError</code> exception, <code>door1.__class__.__dict__['colour']</code></p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
KeyError: 'colour'
door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
'brown'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Indeed, if we compare the objects' equality through the <code>is</code> operator we can confirm that both <code>door1.colour</code> and <code>Door.colour</code> are exactly the same object</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.colour is Door.colour
True
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>When we try to assign a value to a class attribute directly on an instance, we just put in the <code>__dict__</code> of the instance a value with that name, and this value masks the class attribute since it is found first by <code>__getattribute__()</code>. As you can see from the examples of the previous section, this is different from changing the value of the attribute on the class itself.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.colour = 'white'
door1.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
'white'
door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
'brown'
Door.colour = 'red'
door1.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
'white'
door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['colour']
'red'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<h2>Revenge of the Methods</h2>

<p>Let's play the same game with methods. First of all you can see that, just like class attributes, methods are listed only in the class <code>__dict__</code>. Chances are that they behave the same as attributes when we get them</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.open is Door.open
False
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Whoops. Let us further investigate the matter</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.<strong>dict</strong>['open']
<function Door.open at 0xb68604ac>
Door.open
<function Door.open at 0xb68604ac>
door1.open
<bound method Door.open of <__main__.Door object at 0xb67e162c>>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>So, the class method is listed in the members dictionary as <em>function</em>. So far, so good. The same happens when taking it directly from the class; here Python 2 needed to introduce <em>unbound methods</em>, which are not present in Python 3. Taking it from the instance returns a <em>bound method</em>.</p>

<p>Well, a <em>function</em> is a procedure you named and defined with the <code>def</code> statement. When you refer to a function as part of a class in Python 3 you get a plain function, without any difference from a function defined outside a class.</p>

<p>When you get the function from an instance, however, it becomes a bound method. The name <em>method</em> simply means "a function inside an object", according to the usual OOP definitions, while <em>bound</em> signals that the method is linked to that instance. Why does Python bother with methods being bound or not? And how does Python transform a function into a bound method?</p>

<p>First of all, if you try to call a class function you get an error</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.open()
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
TypeError: open() missing 1 required positional argument: 'self'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Yes. Indeed the function was defined to require an argument called 'self', and calling it without an argument raises an exception. This perhaps means that we can give it one instance of the class and make it work</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.open(door1)
door1.status
'open'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Python does not complain here, and the method works as expected. So <code>Door.open(door1)</code> is the same as <code>door1.open()</code>, and this is the difference between a plain function coming from a class an a bound method: the bound method automatically passes the instance as an argument to the function.</p>

<p>Again, under the hood, <code>__getattribute__()</code> is working to make everything work and when we call <code>door1.open()</code>, Python actually calls <code>door1.__class__.open(door1)</code>. However, <code>door1.__class__.open</code> is a plain function, so there is something more that converts it into a bound method that Python can safely call.</p>

<p>When you access a member of an object, Python calls <code>__getattribute__()</code> to satisfy the request. This magic method, however, conforms to a procedure known as <em>descriptor protocol</em>. For the read access <code>__getattribute__()</code> checks if the object has a <code>__get__()</code> method and calls this latter. So the converstion of a function into a bound method happens through such a mechanism. Let us review it by means of an example.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['open']
<function Door.open at 0xb68604ac>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>This syntax retrieves the function defined in the class; the function knows nothing about objects, but it <em>is</em> an object (remember "everything is an object"). So we can look inside it with the <code>dir()</code> built-in function</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>dir(door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['open'])
['<strong>annotations</strong>', '<strong>call</strong>', '<strong>class</strong>', '<strong>closure</strong>', '<strong>code</strong>',
 '<strong>defaults</strong>', '<strong>delattr</strong>', '<strong>dict</strong>', '<strong>dir</strong>', '<strong>doc</strong>', '<strong>eq</strong>',
 '<strong>format</strong>', '<strong>ge</strong>', '<strong>get</strong>', '<strong>getattribute</strong>', '<strong>globals</strong>',
 '<strong>gt</strong>', '<strong>hash</strong>', '<strong>init</strong>', '<strong>kwdefaults</strong>', '<strong>le</strong>', '<strong>lt</strong>',
 '<strong>module</strong>', '<strong>name</strong>', '<strong>ne</strong>', '<strong>new</strong>', '<strong>qualname</strong>', '<strong>reduce</strong>',
 '<strong>reduce_ex</strong>', '<strong>repr</strong>', '<strong>setattr</strong>', '<strong>sizeof</strong>', '<strong>str</strong>',
 '<strong>subclasshook</strong>']
door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['open'].<strong>get</strong>
&lt;method-wrapper '<strong>get</strong>' of function object at 0xb68604ac>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>As you can see, a <code>__get__</code> method is listed among the members of the function, and Python recognizes it as a <em>method-wrapper</em>. This method shall connect the <code>open</code> function to the <code>door1</code> instance, so we can call it passing the instance alone</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['open'].<strong>get</strong>(door1)
<bound method Door.open of <__main__.Door object at 0xb67e162c>>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>and we get exactly what we were looking for. This complex syntax is what happens behind the scenes when we call a method of an instance.</p>

<h2>When Methods met Classes</h2>

<p>Using <code>type()</code> on functions defined inside classes reveals some other details on their internal representation</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>Door.open
<function Door.open at 0xb687e074>
door1.open
<bound method Door.open of <__main__.Door object at 0xb6f9834c>>
type(Door.open)
<class 'function'>
type(door1.open)
<class 'method'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>As you can see, Python tells the two apart recognizing the first as a <em>function</em> and the second as a <em>method</em>, where the second is a function bound to an instance.</p>

<p>What if we want to define a function that operates on the class instead of operating on the instance? As we may define class attributes, we may also define <em>class methods</em> in Python, through the <code>classmethod</code> decorator. Class methods are functions that are bound to the class and not to an instance.</p>

<p>``` python
class Door:</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'brown'

def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.number = number
    self.status = status

@classmethod
def knock(cls):
    print("Knock!")

def open(self):
    self.status = 'open'

def close(self):
    self.status = 'closed'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Such a definition makes the method callable on both the instance and the class</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.knock()
Knock!
Door.knock()
Knock!
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>and Python identifies both as (bound) methods</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.<strong>class</strong>.<strong>dict</strong>['knock']
<classmethod object at 0xb67ff6ac>
door1.knock
<bound method type.knock of <class '__main__.Door'>>
Door.knock
<bound method type.knock of <class '__main__.Door'>>
type(Door.knock)
<class 'method'>
type(door1.knock)
<class 'method'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>As you can see the <code>knock()</code> function accepts one argument, which is called <code>cls</code> just to remember that it is not an instance but the class itself. This means that inside the function we can operate on the class, and the class is shared among instances.</p>

<p>``` python
class Door:</p>

<pre><code>colour = 'brown'

def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.number = number
    self.status = status

@classmethod
def knock(cls):
    print("Knock!")

@classmethod
def paint(cls, colour):
    cls.colour = colour

def open(self):
    self.status = 'open'

def close(self):
    self.status = 'closed'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>paint()</code> classmethod now changes the class attribute <code>colour</code> which is shared among instances. Let's check how it works</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1 = Door(1, 'closed')
door2 = Door(2, 'closed')
Door.colour
'brown'
door1.colour
'brown'
door2.colour
'brown'
Door.paint('white')
Door.colour
'white'
door1.colour
'white'
door2.colour
'white'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>The class method can be called on the class, but this affects both the class and the instances, since the <code>colour</code> attribute of instances is taken at runtime from the shared class.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.paint('yellow')
Door.colour
'yellow'
door1.colour
'yellow'
door2.colour
'yellow'
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Class methods can be called on instances too, however, and their effect is the same as before. The class method is bound to the class, so it works on this latter regardless of the actual object that calls it (class or instance).</p>

<h2>Movie Trivia</h2>

<p>Section titles come from the following movies: <em>The Empire Strikes Back (1980)</em>, <em>Raiders of the Lost Ark (1981)</em>, <em>Revenge of the Nerds (1984)</em>, <em>When Harry Met Sally (1989)</em>.</p>

<h2>Sources</h2>

<p>You will find a lot of documentation in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/226ahl/some_links_about_python_oop/">this Reddit post</a>. Most of the information contained in this series come from those sources.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>Feel free to use <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/b/110554719587236016835/110554719587236016835/posts">the blog Google+ page</a> to comment the post. The <a href="https://github.com/lgiordani/lgiordani.github.com/issues">GitHub issues</a> page is the best place to submit corrections.</p>

<h2>Next post</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-3-delegation-composition-and-inheritance">Python 3 OOP Part 3 - Delegation: composition and inheritance</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python 3 OOP Part 1 - Objects and types]]></title>
    <link href="http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-1-objects-and-types/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T13:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://lgiordani.com/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-1-objects-and-types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--more-->


<h2>About this series</h2>

<p>Object-oriented programming (OOP) has been the leading programming paradigm for several decades now, starting from the initial attempts back in the 60s to some of the most important languages used nowadays. Being a set of programming concepts and design methodologies, OOP can never be said to be "correctly" or "fully" implemented by a language: indeed there are as many implementations as languages.</p>

<p>So one of the most interesting aspects of OOP languages is to understand how they implement those concepts. In this post I am going to try and start analyzing the OOP implementation of the Python language. Due to the richness of the topic, however, I consider this attempt just like a set of thoughts for Python beginners trying to find their way into this beautiful (and sometimes peculiar) language.</p>

<p>This series of posts wants to introduce the reader to the Python 3 implementation of Object Oriented Programming concepts. The content of this and the following posts will not be completely different from that of the previous "OOP Concepts in Python 2.x" series, however. The reason is that while some of the internal structures change a lot, the global philosophy doesn't, being Python 3 an <em>evolution</em> of Python 2 and not a new language.</p>

<p>So I chose to split the previous series and to adapt the content to Python 3 instead of posting a mere list of corrections. I find this way to be more useful for new readers, that otherwise sould be forced to read the previoous series.</p>

<h3>Print</h3>

<p>One of the most noticeable changes introduced by Python 3 is the transformation of the <code>print</code> keyword into the <code>print()</code> function. This is indeed a very small change, compared to other modifications made to the internal structures, but is the most visual-striking one, and will be the source of 80% of your syntax errors when you will start writing Python 3 code.</p>

<p>Remember that print is now a function so write <code>print(a)</code> and not <code>print a</code>.d</p>

<h2>Back to the Object</h2>

<p>Computer science deals with data and with procedures to manipulate that data. Everything, from the earliest Fortran programs to the latest mobile apps is about data and their manipulation.</p>

<p>So if data are the ingredients and procedures are the recipes, it seems (and can be) reasonable to keep them separate.</p>

<p>Let's do some procedural programming in Python</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<h1>This is some data</h1>

<p>data = (13, 63, 5, 378, 58, 40)</p>

<h1>This is a procedure that computes the average</h1>

<p>def avg(d):</p>

<pre><code>return sum(d)/len(d)
</code></pre>

<p>print(avg(data))
```</p>

<p>As you can see the code is quite good and general: the procedure (function) operates on a sequence of data, and it returns the average of the sequence items. So far, so good: computing the average of some numbers leaves the numbers untouched and creates new data.</p>

<p>The observation of the everyday world, however, shows that <em>complex data mutate</em>: an electrical device is on or off, a door is open or closed, the content of a bookshelf in your room changes as you buy new books.</p>

<p>You can still manage it keeping data and procedures separate, for example</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<h1>These are two numbered doors, initially closed</h1>

<p>door1 = [1, 'closed']
door2 = [2, 'closed']</p>

<h1>This procedure opens a door</h1>

<p>def open_door(door):</p>

<pre><code>door[1] = 'open'
</code></pre>

<p>open_door(door1)
print(door1)
```</p>

<p>I described a door as a structure containing a number and the status of the door (as you would do in languages like LISP, for example). The procedure knows how this structure is made and may alter it.</p>

<p>This also works like a charm. Some problems arise, however, when we start building specialized types of data. What happens, for example, when I introduce a "lockable door" data type, which can be opened only when it is not locked? Let's see</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<h1>These are two standard doors, initially closed</h1>

<p>door1 = [1, 'closed']
door2 = [2, 'closed']</p>

<h1>This is a lockable door, initially closed and unlocked</h1>

<p>ldoor1 = [1, 'closed', 'unlocked']</p>

<h1>This procedure opens a standard door</h1>

<p>def open_door(door):</p>

<pre><code>door[1] = 'open'
</code></pre>

<h1>This procedure opens a lockable door</h1>

<p>def open_ldoor(door):</p>

<pre><code>if door[2] == 'unlocked':
    door[1] = 'open'
</code></pre>

<p>open_door(door1)
print(door1)</p>

<p>open_ldoor(ldoor1)
print(ldoor1)
```</p>

<p>Everything still works, no surprises in this code. However, as you can see, I had to find a different name for the procedure that opens a locked door since its implementation differs from the procedure that opens a standard door. But, wait... I'm still opening a door, the action is the same, and it just changes the status of the door itself. So why shall I remember that a locked door shall be opened with <code>open_ldoor()</code> instead of <code>open_door()</code> if the verb is the same?</p>

<p>Chances are that this separation between data and procedures doesn't perfectly fit some situations. The key problem is that the "open" action is not actually <em>using</em> the door; rather it is <em>changing its state</em>. So, just like the volume control buttons of your phone, which are <em>on</em> your phone, the "open" procedure should stick to the "door" data.</p>

<p>This is exactly what leads to the concept of <em>object</em>: an object, in the OOP context, is a structure holding data <em>and</em> procedures operating on them.</p>

<h2>What About Type?</h2>

<p>When you talk about data you immediately need to introduce the concept of <em>type</em>. This concept may have two meanings that are worth being mentioned in computer science: the <em>behavioural</em> and the <em>structural</em> one.</p>

<p>The behavioural meaning represents the fact that you know what something is by describing how it acts. This is the foundation of the so-called "duck typing" (here "typing" means "to give a type" and not "to type on a keyboard"): if it <del>types</del> acts like a duck, it <em>is</em> a duck.</p>

<p>The structural meaning identifies the type of something by looking at its internal structure. So two things that act in the same way but are internally different are of different type.</p>

<p>Both points of view can be valid, and different languages may implement and emphasize one meaning of type or the other, and even both.</p>

<h2>Class Games</h2>

<p>Objects in Python may be built describing their structure through a <em>class</em>. A class is the programming representation of a generic object, such as "a book", "a car", "a door": when I talk about "a door" everyone can understand what I'm saying, without the need of referring to a specific door in the room.</p>

<p>In Python, the type of an object is represented by the class used to build the object: that is, in Python the word <em>type</em> has the same meaning of the word <em>class</em>.</p>

<p>For example, one of the built-in classes of Python is <code>int</code>, which represents an integer number</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>a = 6
print(a)
6
print(type(a))
<class 'int'>
print(a.<strong>class</strong>)
<class 'int'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>As you can see, the built-in function <code>type()</code> returns the content of the <em>magic attribute</em> <code>__class__</code> (magic here means that its value is managed by Python itself offstage). The type of the variable <code>a</code>, or its class, is <code>int</code>. (This is a very inaccurate description of this rather complex topic, so remember that at the moment we are just scratching the surface).</p>

<p>Once you have a class you can <em>instantiate</em> it to get a concrete object (an <em>instance</em>) of that type, i.e. an object built according to the structure of that class. The Python syntax to instantiate a class is the same of a function call</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>b = int()
type(b)
<class 'int'>
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>When you create an instance, you can pass some values, according to the class definition, to <em>initialize</em> it.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>b = int()
print(b)
0
c = int(7)
print(c)
7
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>In this example, the <code>int</code> class creates an integer with value 0 when called without arguments, otherwise it uses the given argument to initialize the newly created object.</p>

<p>Let us write a class that represents a door to match the procedural examples done in the first section</p>

<p>``` python
class Door:</p>

<pre><code>def __init__(self, number, status):
    self.number = number
    self.status = status

def open(self):
    self.status = 'open'

def close(self):
    self.status = 'closed'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>class</code> keyword defines a new class named <code>Door</code>; everything indented under <code>class</code> is part of the class. The functions you write inside the object are called <em>methods</em> and don't differ at all from standard functions; the nomenclature changes only to highlight the fact that those functions now are part of an object.</p>

<p>Methods of a class must accept as first argument a special value called <code>self</code> (the name is a convention but please never break it).</p>

<p>The class can be given a special method called <code>__init__()</code> which is run when the class is instantiated, receiving the arguments passed when calling the class; the general name of such a method, in the OOP context, is <em>constructor</em>, even if the <code>__init__()</code> method is not the only part of this mechanism in Python.</p>

<p>The <code>self.number</code> and <code>self.status</code> variables are called <em>attributes</em> of the object. In Python, methods and attributes are both <em>members</em> of the object and are accessible with the dotted syntax; the difference between attributes and methods is that the latter can be called (in Python lingo you say that a method is a <em>callable</em>).</p>

<p>As you can see the <code>__init__()</code> method shall create and initialize the attributes since they are not declared elsewhere. This is very important in Python and is strictly linked with the way the language handles the type of variables. I will detail those concepts when dealing with polymorphism in a later post.</p>

<p>The class can be used to create a concrete object</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1 = Door(1, 'closed')
type(door1)
<class '__main__.Door'>
print(door1.number)
1
print(door1.status)
closed
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Now <code>door1</code> is an instance of the <code>Door</code> class; <code>type()</code> returns the class as <code>__main__.Door</code> since the class was defined directly in the interactive shell, that is in the current main module.</p>

<p>To call a method of an object, that is to run one of its internal functions, you just access it as an attribute with the dotted syntax and call it like a standard function.</p>

<p>``` python</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>door1.open()
print(door1.number)
1
print(door1.status)
open
```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>In this case, the <code>open()</code> method of the <code>door1</code> instance has been called. No arguments have been passed to the <code>open()</code> method, but if you review the class declaration, you see that it was declared to accept an argument (<code>self</code>). When you call a method of an instance, Python automatically passes the instance itself to the method as the first argument.</p>

<p>You can create as many instances as needed and they are completely unrelated each other. That is, the changes you make on one instance do not reflect on another instance of the same class.</p>

<h2>Recap</h2>

<p>Objects are described by a <em>class</em>, which can generate one or more <em>instances</em>, unrelated each other. A class contains <em>methods</em>, which are functions, and they accept at least one argument called <code>self</code>, which is the actual instance on which the method has been called. A special method, <code>__init__()</code> deals with the initialization of the object, setting the initial value of the <em>attributes</em>.</p>

<h2>Movie Trivia</h2>

<p>Section titles come from the following movies: <em>Back to the Future (1985)</em> , <em>What About Bob? (1991)</em>, <em>Wargames (1983)</em>.</p>

<h2>Sources</h2>

<p>You will find a lot of documentation in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/226ahl/some_links_about_python_oop/">this Reddit post</a>. Most of the information contained in this series come from those sources.</p>

<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>Feel free to use <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/b/110554719587236016835/110554719587236016835/posts">the blog Google+ page</a> to comment the post. The <a href="https://github.com/lgiordani/lgiordani.github.com/issues">GitHub issues</a> page is the best place to submit corrections.</p>

<h2>Next post</h2>

<p><a href="/blog/2014/08/20/python-3-oop-part-2-classes-and-members">Python 3 OOP Part 2 - Classes and members</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
